A spiritually enriching period is approaching Chaturmas, the holy union of the four holiest Hindu months,
Shravan, Bhadrapat, Ashwin and Karting.
It begins on 6 July and continues until 2 November.
Understanding the significance of this divine period is essential for every seeker.
Let's understand in simple words how one can derive the maximum spiritual benefit from Chaturmas.
Commencing on Devchani Ekadashi in the month of Ashad
and concluding on Devchani Ekadashi, Chaturmas offers a golden opportunity to gain spiritual wealth.
During these four months Lord Narayana enters yogic sleep, that's Yognidra
and becomes deeply absorbed in his Brahminic state, hence chanting austerity, sacred bathing,
vows, fasting undertaken during this time, yield many fold results compared to other days.
Let us understand six or species acts to be performed during Chaturmas.
First, doing noble deeds that Satkarma.
Second, listening to divine discourses that Sat-San Bhagwatkatha.
Third, serving saints. Fourth, taking darshan of saints and attending Sat-San.
Fifth, worshipping the Lord with devotion. Sixth, engaging in charity.
Each of these acts is said to yield immeasurable spiritual rewards.
Now let us understand what should be practiced during Chaturmas.
Those who observe celibacy and sleep on the ground during these four months accumulate immeasurable merit
and attain exceptional spiritual progress.
One who eats only once a day throughout Chaturmas becomes free from disease, gains spiritual strength
and earns the merit of performing the sacred Agnistom Yajna leading to divine reams.
Observing vows and disciplines during this period grants one the merit of a thousand Ashwameda Yajnas.
Reciting the Vishnu Sastranama or Purushasukthaam during this time brings both spiritual merit and powerful speech.
Drinking Panchagavya, that's a sacred Ayurvedic preparation made up mainly of Kaayurine.
During Chaturmas is considered highly purifying and beneficial for health.
Now let us understand what should be renounced during Chaturmas.
No wedding or auspicious worldly ceremonies should be performed during this period.
Renouncing curd helps maintain good health and leads to Goloka attainment,
that is, divine reams attainment. Renouncing salt brings in her purification and freedom from
sins. Giving up jaggery leads to the attainment of a sweet nature. Renouncing honey, coconut,
pomegranate, urad dal, chickpeas, enhances one's spiritual merit.
Avoid using copper and bronze utensils. Instead, it meals on palash leaves which brings the fruit
of observing chandraena and ikadashi fasts. Take a vow to refrain from marital intimacy and
completely refrain from engaging in gossip, both speaking and hearing it.
If you are still watching this video, be sure to share this valuable information with others.
And if you have any questions, please leave them in the comments. Every effort will be made to respond.
Hario.